<chapter id="gettingstarted">
    <title>Getting Started with Facelets</title>

    <sect1 id="gettingstarted-download">
        <title>Downloading Facelets</title>
        <para>
			Facelets is currently available as a sub-project of the JavaServer Faces Reference Implementation on Java.net (http://facelets.dev.java.net/).  You have a couple options for downloading Facelets:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				Download a release binary from http://facelets.dev.java.net/servlets/ProjectDocumentList.  Once downloaded, unzip the project into an appropriate folder.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					If you are a member of Java.net, you may checkout Facelets from CVS.  Make sure you are located in the appropriate directory and use the following CVS commands (Replace <literal>USER_NAME</literal> with your Java.net Member Login Name):
				</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<literal>cvs -d :pserver:USER_NAME@cvs.dev.java.net:/cvs login</literal>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<literal>cvs -d :pserver:USER_NAME@cvs.dev.java.net:/cvs checkout facelets</literal>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
				<para>
					More information on accessing Java.net's CVS repository is located at http://facelets.dev.java.net/servlets/ProjectSource. 
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			See TODO for more information on building Facelets from source (specifically if you used CVS).
		</para>
    </sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="gettingstarted-jsf">
		<title>Dependencies</title>
		<para>
			Facelets will work with both version 1.1 and 1.2 of JavaServer Faces and makes no bearing on the implementation used.  Facelets also uses the new EL-API and again can be used with any implementation of that API.  Please reference the table below to make sure your dependencies are available to Facelets:
		</para>
		<table>
			<title>Facelets Dependencies</title>
			<tgroup cols="4">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Project</entry>
						<entry>Build Req?</entry>
						<entry>Included?</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Link</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>JavaServer Faces RI</entry>
						<entry>No</entry>
						<entry>No</entry>
						<entry>The reference implementation of JSF 1.1 and JSF 1.2 are available for use with your application.</entry>
						<entry>https://javaserverfaces.dev.java.net/</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Apache MyFaces</entry>
						<entry>No</entry>
						<entry>No</entry>
						<entry>The alternative to the JSF reference implementation.  MyFaces currently implements the JSF 1.1 specification.</entry>
						<entry>http://myfaces.apache.org/</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>JavaServer Faces 1.2 API</entry>
						<entry>Yes</entry>
						<entry>No</entry>
						<entry>JSF 1.2 API that works with the new EL Specification.  This API is packaged with the JavaServer Faces RI and available on Java.net.</entry>
						<entry>https://javaserverfaces.dev.java.net/</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>EL API</entry>
						<entry>Yes</entry>
						<entry>Yes</entry>
						<entry>The standardized EL specification that is standalone from JSP or JSF, but used by both frameworks.</entry>
						<entry>https://glassfish.dev.java.net/</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>EL RI</entry>
						<entry>No</entry>
						<entry>Yes</entry>
						<entry>The reference implementation that is used by Facelets for handling EL.</entry>
						<entry>https://glassfish.dev.java.net/</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>XML SAX</entry>
						<entry>Yes</entry>
						<entry>No</entry>
						<entry>This dependency should not be an issue for most deployments as it's a standard part of web containers and JREs.</entry>
						<entry>http://java.sun.com/xml/</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<para>
			For more information on using these projects:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Those projects that are required to build Facelets, please see TODO
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					If you would like to use Apache MyFaces with Facelets, see TODO
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					To use Facelets with the JavaServer Faces Reference Implementation, see TODO
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	
</chapter>


